Guide to the David Wagstaff Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
David Wagstaff papers
1824-1950
GEN MSS 415
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.7
(10 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 1 portfolio, cold storage
Collection consists of personal papers and materials collected by David Wagstaff. Included are diaries of Wagstaff's travels from 1907-1921; correspondence, organizational papers, photographs and other materials related to the Ristigouche Salmon Club and the Restigouche Riparian Association; personal papers including catalog cards of Wagstaff's book collection; and materials generally concerning hunting and fishing collected by Wagstaff,including shooting targets, shooting awards, photographs of unidentified individuals, generally from the nineteenth century, one photograph album of the United States Military Academy (West Point) class of 1861, and one album of members of the 1867 New York (State) Legislature Assembly.
Wagstaff, David, 1882-1951
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Isabelle (Mrs. David) Wagstaff and the Wagstaff Estate, 1951 and 1958.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile materials in the portfolio and in cold storage may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files. One original negative came with the papers. A copy print has been made and the original stored separately.
DAVID WAGSTAFF, 1882-1951
David Wagstaff was born in 1882. He received his B.A. from Harvard in 1905, and worked as a partner in the New York City brokerage firm of Dominick & Dominick from 1915-1929. An avid sportsman, he collected sporting books, paintings, and prints, many of which he later donated to the University of Virginia and to Yale University. From 1943-1951 he served as the Curator of Sporting Books in the Yale University Library. He died in 1951.
Scope and Contents
The David Wagstaff Papers contain personal papers and materials collected by David Wagstaff, including travel diaries, papers related to fishing on the Restigouche River in the province of Québec, catalog cards of Wagstaff's collection of sporting books, photographs, shooting targets and awards. The Papers have been arranged into two series; Personal Papers and Materials Collected by David Wagstaff. The Papers span the years 1824-1950, but the bulk of the materials date from the period 1907-1950.
Series I, Personal Papers, contains travel diaries, materials related to the Restigouche Riparian Associations, materials related to the Ristigouche Salmon Club in Matapédia, Québec, of which Wagstaff was a member, and other papers. The travel diaries document cruises and trips taken by Wagstaff between 1907-1921. Many of the diaries include photographs of the scenery, Wagstaff's companions and the fish they caught. The Restigouche Riparian Association materials consist of annual reports, records of fish caught by local fishing groups and individuals, treasurer's reports, and other papers. The Ristigouche Salmon Club materials contain correspondence, organizational records, financial records, and photographs. Included are letters from the Club and its members to David Wagstaff, generally concerning the Club's plans for the fishing season and the state of the Club and the Restigouche River. Also included are copies of letters from the Club to various members. The organizational records include annual reports, fishing records, and fishing rules and regulations. Financial records consist of bills and receipts sent to Wagstaff for membership fees and other Club-related expenses. The photographs include pictures of Club members and staff, and scenes of the Club and the Restigouche River area. Other personal papers include blank Christmas cards from Wagstaff and his wife Isabelle, hunting and fishing licenses, a scrapbook of newspaper clippings entitled "In Memoriam. Wesley Hunt Tilford," the Last Will and Testament of an earlier David Wagstaff, and catalog cards of Wagstaff's collection of sporting books.
Series II, Materials Collected by David Wagstaff, contains materials related to hunting, fishing and shooting, generally from the nineteenth century. Included are clippings from newspapers and magazines about hunting and fishing, programs for shooting competitions, and illustrated shooting targets and awards. Photographs include portraits of men and a woman in various shooting poses, a rifle match, a portrait of the American Rifle Team of 1880, and two photograph albums: one with portraits and signatures of members of the New York (State) Legislature Assembly of 1867, and one containing portraits of the United States Military Academy (West Point) class of 1861.
Book collecting; Fishing; Hunting; Salmon fishing; Shooting; Matapédia River Valley (Québec); Restigouche River (N.B. and Québec); Diaries; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Wagstaff, David, 1882-1951; New York (State). Legislature. Assembly -- Pictorial works; Restigouche Riparian Association; Ristigouche Salmon Club (Matapédia, Québec); United States Military Academy. Class of 1861
- Personal Papers, 1824-1950; Series I; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  - TRAVEL DIARIES
    - "Cruise of 1907" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "East Coast, Shark River and Madeira Bay," with photographs, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "The Heron. From Fort Myers to Shark River and Return," with photographs, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Florida West Coast", 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - "Trip of 1909. The Whim. Texas, Louisiana and Mississippi" (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Cruise of 1911. Savale[?] and Ellis J." (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Cruise of 1912" (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Cruise of 1913" (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Cruise of 1914" (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Cruise of 1915" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Cruise of 1916," with photographs (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Cruise of 1917" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Cruise of 1918" (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Cruise of 1919" (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "1920" (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Cruise of 1921" (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - RESTIGOUCHE RIPARIAN ASSOCIATION
    - Annual reports, 1925-40 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Records of fish caught in area rivers, 1924-35 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1924-35 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Other Papers, 1927-31, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - RISTIGOUCHE SALMON CLUB
    - Correspondence
      Scope and Contents
      Letters to David Wagstaff
      - Chestnut Canoe Co., Limited, 1945 Jul 27 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Johnson, Percy H., 1949 Mar 30 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Leyman, Harry S., 1946 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Metallic, Edward, 1948 Sep 14 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Ristigouche Salmon Club, 1921-50 (Box 3, Folder 26-33)
        Includes: Letters from Howard Baetjer, Guy Cary and J. F. Rooney
        Includes: Drafts of the Club's Annual Report, 1933 and 1942, and the Fishing Rules of 1936
      - Tilford, Henry Morgan, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Van Horne, J.C., 1950 Jan 20 (Box 3, Folder 35)
        Includes: Map of a section of the Matapédia, Québec area
      - Webster, George B., 1948 Sep (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Wells, Bulkeley L., 1930 Aug 13 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Ziegler, J. M., 1941 May 7 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Unidentified, 1945 Sep 6 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Ristigouche Salmon Club Correspondence
        - Baetjer, Edwin G., 1942 Dec 10 (Box 3, Folder 40)
        - Bell, James F., 1943 Nov 30 (Box 3, Folder 41)
        - General club membership, 1937-50 (Box 3, Folder 42)
        - Leyman, Harry S., 1942-46 (Box 3, Folder 43)
          Includes: Letters from the Outboard Marine and Manufacturing Company
        - Phelps, Earle Bernard, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 44)
        - Rooney, J. F., 1941, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 45)
        - Unidentified, 1936 Sep 2 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Other Correspondence
        - De Forest, Henry W. to Oliver S. Campbell, 1934 Oct 15 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Organizational Records
      - Annual reports, 1923-49 (Box 4, Folder 48-51)
      - Individual members' fishing records, 1926-50 (Box 4, Folder 52-53)
        Includes: Letter from the Club to Wagstaff
      - Club fishing records, 1906-26 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Fishing rules and regulations, 1907-43 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Matapédia Bridge Gauge. Records of water height, 1920-49 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Results of fishing seasons, 1925-50 (Box 4, Folder 57-58)
      - "Suggested Fishing Rules for 1943 Season" (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Up-river occupation charts, 1930-49 (Box 4, Folder 60-61)
      - Other papers, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Financial Records
      - Bills for club expenses, 1925-49 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Receipts for club expenses, 1934-47 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - Membership fee receipts, 1924-49 (Box 4, Folder 65)
      - Other bills, 1939-45 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      - Other financial papers, 1932-44 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Photographs
      - "Brown trout. Speared January 30th 1929. Canal. Southside Sportsmen's Club. Oakdale, N.Y." (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - Clusser, Renfer, with fish, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - "Coming into Indian House[?]" (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - "The 'Elm' at Patapédia [sic]", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 71)
      - "Indian House[?] down river" (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - "Looking down from Pine[?] Island" (Box 4, Folder 73)
      - "Matapédia Bridge", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - "Matapédia Pool", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - "Red Bank - Joe Furlot", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - "The 'Rock' with Mr. Pratt", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - Unidentified building, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - Unidentified men, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - Unidentified water scenes, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Christmas cards from David and Isabelle Wagstaff (Box 5, Folder 81-82)
    - Hunting and fishing licenses, 1919-47 (Box 5, Folder 83-85)
    - "In Memoriam. Wesley Hunt Tilford," album of newspaper clippings, [1909?]
    - Last Will and Testament of an earlier David Wagstaff, 1824, 1828
    - Notes removed from the travel diary "Cruise of 1917" (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Photographs removed from the travel diary "Cruise of 1917" (Box 5, Folder 87-88)
    - "Southside Sportsmen's Club. Oakdale, Long Island," rules and reports, 1932-41 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - "Tuxedo Park, New York. Fishing Rules", 1932 Apr 1 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Unidentified envelope addressed to Wagstaff, 1943 Jun 29 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Wagstaff, David. Newspaper clipping of a letters to the editor of an unidentified paper, 1933 Feb 25 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Catalog cards of items in Wagstaff's book and manuscript collection donated to Yale, ca. 1950-55 (Box 6, Folder 93)
- Materials Collected by David Wagstaff, 1867-1899; Series II; 0.4; (3 boxes)
  - HUNTING AND FISHING PAPERS
    - Clippings from newspapers and magazines about hunting and fishing (Box 7, Folder 94-95)
    - Programs for shooting competitions[?], 1879, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Shooting awards, 1872-82, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 97-98)
    - Shooting targets, 1879-99, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 99-100)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - American Rifle Team, 1880 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Bryant Testimonial Vase, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Portrait of a man signed "Gilbert Bacon", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - "Nynark. Peekskill. Central Valley... Rifle Match", 1886, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Unidentified military unit in target practice, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Unidentified portrait of a family, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Unidentified portraits of men, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 107-108)
    - Unidentified men with guns, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Unidentified woman with gun, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - PHOTOGRAPH ALBUMS
    - "Album of the Assembly, New York 1867," photograph album with portraits and signatures of members of the New York (State) Legislature Assembly (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Photograph album of the United States Military Academy (West Point) class of 1861, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 112)
- Oversize, 0.8; (1 box) + 2 broadside folders
  - Up-river occupation charts (in Series I), 1930-49 (Box bsd, folder 113)
  - Last Will and Testament of an earlier David Wagstaff (in Series I), 1824, 1828 (Box bsd, folder 114)
  - "In Memoriam. Wesley Hunt Tilford," album of newspaper clippings (in Series I), [1909?] (Box 10, Folder 115)
- Restricted Fragile
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult appropriate curator.
  - Box 3, folder 26 (Box port, Folder 116)
  - Box 3, folder 28 (Box port, Folder 117)
  - Box 3, folder 29 (Box port, Folder 118)
  - Box 3, folder 47 (Box port, Folder 119)
  - Box 5, folder 86 (Box port, Folder 120)
  - Box 4, folder 79 (Box cs, Folder 121)